Welcome back everybody to the three
question series from the Alliance for
Mission and Renewal. I'm Chris Gordon
and I am here with someone that I'm
excited for you to meet. This is Denine
Blevens and she's about to tell you all
kinds of good things. So, why don't you
go ahead and introduce yourself?
>> Yeah, I would love to. Thanks,
Christine. I am Denine Blevens. I live
in New York City with my husband Robert
um and our little dog Sydney. Robert is
the director of Mercy Ministries under
the M under um Mission to North America
and um yeah, we've been married for
about nine years. We love our city. We
love our dog and we love the gospel and
mission.
>> You know, I'm going to have to ask you
what kind of dog Sydney is just as
>> So, don't judge us, but we did get her
DNA tested [laughter] because I really
wanted to know. So, she's like half
beagle, half terrier, and like 2%
poodle. And she's literally the cutest
dog ever.
>> Everybody says so in our neighborhood.
>> Oh, I mean obviously
>> we had nothing to do with it.
>> I believe you. I am a dog person. All
right. So Sydney is with us in spirit.
So can you answer our three questions
for us? First, what is your little
corner of the kingdom that you're
working right now?
>> Yes. So I serve as the executive
director of Paracleo which is a
nonprofit organization that provides
relational support and learning for
women who serve on church planning teams
especially the wives of church planners.
Um, we started off as a ministry under
Mission to North America back in 2005,
specifically serving church planners
wives in the PCA. But then over the
years, we expanded. So, we're now our
own 501c3 organization. We serve
different denominations and countries um
in the US, Latin America, Asia Pacific,
and now for the first time Europe,
mostly in partnership with church
planning networks. Um, so this morning I
got to be on a Zoom call with leaders
from church plants across my city. Had
nothing to do with paracleo to talk
about a children's like a children's
initiative. And I looked at the faces of
all these enthusiastic young men and
women and thought you guys have no idea
what you're about to face. [laughter]
Um cuz we've seen like all the pressures
and demands of church planning and it
just can be so overwhelming. It's like
this pressure cooker. you do so much
with a limited um limited time, limited
people, limited resources, and if you
don't do something to let that pressure
>> um unleash, you know, it can just really
have devastating results. Um so that the
expectations of planning is high. So
this is true for the lean planter, but
it's also true for the wives that
sacrifice so much, but they're often so
overlooked.
>> Yes. Wow. And even be even being on your
web page is amazing. The the levels of
support that you can give is just so
encouraging to even read about. Okay.
So, tell us tell us a story about what
God's been doing through you and your
ministry lately. Give us a little
little, you know, pull back the curtain
for us a little bit.
>> Yeah, sure. Um I was thinking about with
general assembly last year. There were
two women who came into our booth and
they were friends. Um they they I think
they had served at the same church and
then both of their husbands had felt
called to start other churches went
through assessment and got you know got
the green light to go. So they were
moving to these different city to plant
churches. They were both excited
>> and also completely overwhelmed by what
they're about to face. Um, one of them
talked about talked about the
expectations from the people in her
church, the loneliness that she was
feeling and the lack of support that
existed for her, especially in
comparison to her husband who was part
of a a church planning network um and a
supportive group for him. So, they had
both heard about paracleo but had never
been able to participate because the re
everything was in English and these are
two Spanish speakers. So, we conducted
this whole conversation in Spanish. Um,
it just so happens, Christine, that we
have been praying about starting a
cohort for Spanish speakers in the
United States and had already translated
our new materials for that. Um, our
program director is fluent in Spanish
and we had another leader who was ready
to go that also shared this burden. So
within months, these two womens who
women who were like, we've heard about
Barakle for years, we've never been able
to do it. They were in their very first
community called aragadas which means
rooted in Spanish. So it was it was same
paracle materials but written for them
especially for Spanish speaking women
dealing with the realities of living in
the United States. And so what struck me
with that is that God had already been
at work answering a prayer that they
probably hadn't even prayed yet.
>> Um and so that group Aradus that started
last year and they're just about to do
their third module called Gaining
Perspective.
I don't even know what to say to that
other than
>> I know.
>> Wow. And God knows. And how encouraging
it must be for you to even look on the
faces of these women and be able to in
that moment go, "Oh, God knew. He
already knew you were coming. He got you
ready for us." What a Thank you. What a
wonderful story.
>> So, as we I'm sure you could tell us
lots and lots of more stories. So, as we
your brothers and sisters out here in
the PCA, you're in New York and we're
like everywhere.
>> How can we support you and the work of
Paracleo? There's what can we do?
>> Yeah. I mean, Paracleo is is not just my
job like it it it was a lifeline for me
when I was not the wife of a church
planner, when I was on a church planning
team as a single woman at the time,
helping to carry all the weight and
burden of the church, but just didn't
have any support. And so I was able to
get into a paracleo group. And so this
is um for me the best way to support me
is is by supporting our mission not just
through paracleo but through supporting
women in church planning across the
board. Um our vision is to see women and
men follow Christ to grow churches that
bear fruit um that bear lasting fruit.
So we intentionally put women first in
our vision statement, not because we
think we're better, but because they've
often been thought of last when it comes
to supporting them.
>> So I would ask our brothers and sisters
that are listening to think of women.
That's that's the best way that you can
encourage this work. Think of women.
Sometimes in our excitement um
supporting the important and beautiful
work of church planning efforts across
our denomination, we can forget about
the women who are the backbone of these
efforts who are on the ground behind the
scene doing the things in and day in day
out but are just struggling because they
feel lonely and unsupported and having
to carry all this on their own um or
feel like they do. And so for people
that are in authority positions such as
church planners, what is your plan for
caring for your wife? Like think about
her. If if you're a network leader,
church planning network leader, what
supportive systems are you building for
wives and female staff members? it it
when you partner with us, it really
doesn't take much, but to just to be
thinking about that if you're in a
position of funding, like maybe you're
an emissions team, is there an a
proportional amount of funding being set
aside for women, not equal, because we
recognize that men are the lead
planners? And so we want to make sure
that that the majority resources are for
them for the long haul, but there should
be an a proportional amount for women
who are who are whether they're heavily
involved in the church plant or more
behind the scenes. The emotional support
that she provides to her husband as the
lead planter or to the other members of
the core team is just really
indispensable. And if she goes down,
everybody goes down. So invest in her.
Um, and then finally, if you're watching
this and you're the the the um church
planner's wife or maybe you're a female
staff member that's really involved on a
church planning team, I want to
encourage you to think about yourself.
>> You know, one of the best ways that you
can serve your church plan is to is to
dedicate time for you, for your own
spiritual well-being. invest in
relationships um for yourself outside
the church that nourish you and make
sure that you're getting your weekly
Sabbath even if you can only get away
for a couple of hours and just making
that intentional and just remember that
there's a community built just for you
in paracleo. So those are the things
that if if people watching this would
apply these things that would actually
encourage me and it also do would do so
much for church planning culture.
>> Did you hear her? That's from Denine.
She's not messing around y'all. These
are the things we need to do. And
there's so much more. There's so many.
There's so many helps. Even just in
these few minutes, you can hear them.
You can hear the rich resources here.
Thank you so much for telling us. And
where if they if they're just hearing
and they're like, "Oh, where do I go? I
know I need something. What's What's the
fastest way to find you?"
>> Yeah, I'm sure we'll post it, but just
go to our website. That's the starting
place. Um and you'll see a list of
program offerings that we have. We're
kicking off our fall series. Also,
follow us on Instagram and on Facebook
so that you can get it's not just um
things for you to it's it's not more for
you to do. It's encouragement for your
own heart. So, [clears throat] yeah.
>> Thank you so much, Janine. Thank you for
your work. Thanks for watching
everybody.